special privileges for me to welcome all
of you to Finn's first event
Poseidon's illusion challenging the way
we see marine sustainability is also my
great pleasure to welcome our two
speakers this evening dr. arthur hansen
and dr. jordan peterson I'll be speaking
a little bit more about each of these
gentlemen later on in the program but
what I would like to say now is from my
experience working with dr. Peterson and
from what I've seen it heard about dr.
arthur hansen these are two true
renaissance men and we are very excited
to have him here this evening so before
I get to our speakers I'm going to tell
you a little bit about Finn Finn is not
your conventional environmental
organization all of our executive
members have a background in psychology
as opposed to engineering environmental
studies or biology now this leads to
some special benefits that we have I'm
going to tell you about three different
oh well the special benefits are that we
can use our knowledge of the brain
emotion and behavior to develop
innovative angles on how to publicize
the problem of marine life decimation so
I'm going to tell you about three
different psychological concepts that we
try to integrate into our advertising
over the past couple months so the first
is that images of cute animals induce
positive emotion and neuro attentional
focus that's probably not what you were
expecting to see
Fred the fish doesn't quite do it for
you does he so we had to be a little bit
creative
we had to approach this problem that
fish and their appearance don't really
draw that fuzzy emotion from you that
you really want to help them out that's
probably a lot better so we took the
approach that if I don't know if any of
you have pets but you know that when
their food bowl is full we're pretty
happy now if you take that food away
like for example if fish were to
suddenly be gone which is one of their
food sources not so happy now you got a
slogan to it there you go that's one of
our first advertisements so the second
concept that I'm going to go over is one
that we've actually borrowed from social
psychology research and that's something
that's called the door in the face
technique so the gist of this technique
is that you initially make a large
request from an individual that's
probably going to be shut down that's
probably going to be the answer that
you're going to get so then you follow
up this request with a much smaller more
reasonable one of course they're going
to so the reason behind that is that an
individual is more likely to agree to
the second more reasonable request what
is R appreciated by an outlandish one
versus has it hadn't been asked on its
own so the final concept that I'm going
to go over it's going to require a
little bit of background knowledge which
I'm going to discuss and it's an angle
that we decide to take about the health
benefits that you receive when you
ingest fish or possibly fish oil now I
imagine that many of you know who this
is this is sy he's best known for his
dancing Gangnam style if you don't know
him you can ask for students on Monday
potentially your children tonight
they're very familiar with him
so Gangnam style is essentially a well
refers to a district in Seoul South
Korea and the people who live there they
have a very affluent lifestyle and they
achieve this wealth pretty much
overnight they didn't exactly have to
work for so because of this it's often
related to this aphorism with great
power comes great responsibility because
of the fact that they didn't have to
work for their wealth and it came
overnight they don't really have a sense
of their social responsibility so we
decided to take this and related to
finish when it comes to eating fish
we're all living Gangnam style basically
what this means is that we were born
into a world that has oceans that were
kind of this brave resource it was we
were rich with fish but because of this
we didn't really develop at the same
time that sense of responsibility that
we have to maintain our oceans and
maintain their sense sustainability so
now to the psychological concept this
author is in that we decided to use it
wasn't enough we wanted to take it one
step further that's what we're always
doing we're really really pushing so
when you eat fish it helps with early
brain development and the prevention or
treatment of brain related problems so
again referring to the food chain like
we did before how cats they eat fish we
have to think who really wants a good
healthy bringing zombies zombies eat
brains and they want them to be good as
opposed to unhealthy and we're lucky
because in Toronto we have a lot of
zombies so you add that to the fact that
people like to dance Gangnam style
and now just to summarize and make sure
that you're following me you have Tom
B's who need good brains and because of
that they need fish you add that to
dancing Gangnam style you add that to
the author ISM that we developed about
fish and how we're all living Gangnam
style and the next logical progression
that we were going to do zombies dancing
gang
style bearing fish shirts with the
catchphrase at the end now you'd be
surprised to know that we were actually
beaten to the punch there is already a
zombie that dances Gangnam style and he
does a pretty good Michael Jackson and
Elvis Presley as well so we had to dog
we have to pitch this idea but on a
serious note this really has been one of
the most rewarding but challenging
projects I have had the opportunity to
work on you soon learn that one-tenth of
the battle is pulling together the
correct data the rest is communication
and finding ways to make people listen
something that I quickly learned while
growing up and trying to get my parents
to see things my way
is that everyone has a different
perspective and way of communicating
though we all may speak a particular
language when it comes to explaining a
problem or inspiring action different
things make sense and push different
people for some it is art such as image
or dance for others it is an equation or
a graph for some it is comedy and even
others reading and logic it is fin
school to use all of these mediums to
raise public awareness about the
decimation of marine life then with the
help of every believer we want to
inspire change in Canada's ocean
management policy now this is something
that we do not plan to do by ourselves
either we hope to create links not only
between departments within the
University of Toronto but also between
all forms of post-secondary institutions
across Canada the Arts and Design
schools as well as science and research
institutions in this way we can reach
out not only to communities
geographically across Canada but also to
the communities of like-minded reasoning
so on that note I would like to
introduce now our first speaker dr.
Jordan Peterson he earns
here in his PhD in psychology at McGill
University and following his post dr.
doctoral fellowship at McGill's Douglas
Hospital served as a professor of
psychology at Harvard four years later
he came to the University of Toronto
where he is a professor with two main
areas of study the psychology of belief
and the assessment and improvement of
personality his work has been supported
by all three of the main Canadian
granting agencies as well as the Rotman
Business School Center for Integrative
thinking he is authored and co-authored
over 70 scientific articles including
one book maps of meaning the
architecture of belief and soon to be a
second 42
dr. Pearson holds multiple order and
teaching awards including a nomination
for the Levinson teaching Prize at
Harvard in 1998 and nominations by TVO
as one of Ontario's best university
lectures each year from 2005 to 2008 in
addition to his clinical practice dr.
Peterson serves as a business consultant
an executive coach for senior partners
of large law firms in Toronto and is the
vice-president of a personality
assessment and remediation company he is
also a frequent guest panelist on TVO's
the agenda and a popular source of
information for other TV shows radio
programs and printed articles please
welcome a man who through the years has
inspired thousands of students to pursue
their dreams and instill the belief in
the members of Finn that we can
accomplish anything so why not
immediately start trying
thanks Christine so anyways it looks to
me like that's what we're facing over
the next few decades
it's kind of an evocative phrase the
seat seems empty anyways because of
course you can't see what's beneath the
surface but before the depredations of
people it was an amazing resource I
started to learn about this and I'm
going to walk you through what I learned
because I think it's a reasonable way of
introducing everyone to the basic
elements of familiarity that are
necessary to understand what's happening
in the oceans I guess sometimes I've
noticed that it's useful when you're
teaching people not to know a lot more
than your audience does because if you
start to develop great expertise in an
area then you forget what people don't
know and it's easy to speak about things
that aren't easy to follow and you
shouldn't have any problem with that
tonight because as I said I'm a relative
beginner in this area and a lot of the
things I learned were really quite
obvious things especially in retrospect
but I didn't know them I got an
opportunity to start familiarizing
myself with this particular issue
because I was fortunate enough to work
with the Canadian subcommittee that a
second Secretary General of the UN set
up about three years ago and the
secretary-general was interested in
producing a report and this is the final
report resilient people resilient planet
and it was sort of a follow up to the
1992 Brundtland Commission which was the
first real worldwide attempt to bring
some order and intelligence to
ecological issues some with a certain
degree of success now that was followed
up in Brazil in 2012 with an ecological
/ economic meeting that wasn't precisely
a raving success but this was the
document that
served as lead up to the 2012 20th
anniversary of the of the Brundtland
Commission and the reason I was asked to
serve on this committee was because the
people who ran it it was headed by Jim
Balsillie who ran REM Corporation the
people who ran it didn't think that the
underlying narrative of the report was
appropriate for the modern day and in
some sense it sort of felt like it had
been written in 1984 which is actually
quite a long time ago now there was a
lot of North versus South ideology in it
an ideology that's less relevant now
that the less developed world is
developing at an incredible rate and
there was a lot of left versus right
ideology in it when it seems more
appropriate in the modern world to note
that problems of this magnitude have to
be solved by everyone regardless of
their political orientation and there
was a lot of underlying the underlying
implicit idea that the planet would be
better off without people on it which is
not a position that I hold and which I
also think is a dangerous one to promote
and so I have the opportunity to
rephrase the underlying structure of the
document to some degree to the degree
that that's possible when you're working
with multiple committees but but at
least in part to stress some of the
really great things that people have
accomplished over the last two decades
and I want to start with that because
it's necessary to put things in context
you know what I mean we're assaulted by
apocalypses all the time I mean I'm 50
years old now and I mean I can I've
lived through at least five probable
apocalypses none of which thankfully
occurred and the problem with that is
that it's easy to get apocalypse
overdose and in a sense and to feel that
you're assaulted by catastrophes from so
many directions that the only logical
thing to do is to ignore them now I
don't think that's true because people
have been getting their act together in
multiple dimensions in quite remarkable
ways and so I'll detail some of those in
1970 approximately 900 of the 3.5
billion people currently
we're hungry the same number we're
hungry in 2008 however the population
had doubled during that period so the
proportion of hungry people have during
the most rapid expansion of human
population in history that's pretty
remarkable and is it not what people
predicted because the most dire
environmental estimates in the late
1960s were predicated on the idea that
by the year 2000 with the 6 or 7 billion
people that were likely to be around
that there would be widespread
starvation
quite the contrary people are better fed
than they ever have been in fact there
are more obese people in the world now
than there are hungry people which is
really some kind of accomplishment even
though it's you know damning in a sense
with failure praise in 1981 about 52% of
the world's population 2 billion of 4.5
lived under the new world bank poverty
cutoff estimates of $1 in quarter a day
by 2005 that figure had decreased to 25%
and current estimates indicate that this
figure is moving downwards at 2 percent
of the total world population per year
assuming 1.5 percent which is
conservative the percentage below the
poverty cutoff by now may have fallen to
15 percent so that's a staggering
achievement the proportion of people
living in poverty in East Asia in the
Pacific is decreased by more than 50
percent since 1990 and this after rates
had already have in the previous two
decades lifespan has increased
dramatically we have the spectacle in
Africa now where I read The Economist a
week and a half ago that there are
enough cell phones in Africa now so that
3 out of 4 people have them and that's
brought tremendous economic advantages
to the people of Africa contributing in
part to the fact which is almost
impossible to believe that the
sub-saharan African countries are now
the fastest growing economies in the
world and so we're actually in a
position maybe for the first time in
human history where the only reason for
starvation and hunger is political so
there's also been a staggering decrease
in the number of anti-democratic or
totalitarian States over the last 30
years and it's partly because
in some sense the whole idea of
totalitarianism whether it's on the left
or the right has lost its essential
validity even the dictators themselves
don't believe in there in the
justifications they put forward for
their abuse of power and so what we've
seen happening is horrible governments
toppling one after another at what's
really a miraculous rate you know and
that's all on top of the collapse of the
Soviet Union and you know the demolition
of the Iron Curtain and all these things
that for someone my age seemed
absolutely miraculous not not to mention
of course the opening up of China so you
know three cheers for the human race
it's pretty damn good that we've managed
to put those sort of successes together
I mean the UN had a millennium goal in
2000 to cut poverty in the world by half
by 2015 they figured they hit that by
2011 so you know these things are just
any any person with any sense would
regard that fundamentally as miraculous
its massive economic productivity
increases combined with massive
population increases I mean so you know
it's not all gloomy and so the UN and
the initial UN record have virtually
none of that in there I think that's a
real mistake you know because human
beings you know we've got waste
management problems and there's a lot of
us and we eat a lot but you know we're
also trying as hard as we can before
things together as fast as we can you
know all things considered is always
unreasonable people but you know for a
bunch of creatures that only separated
from chimpanzees 7 million years ago you
know we're not doing that bad we didn't
even understand oceanic ecology at all
you know for acceptance into the last
hundred years so we are trying to learn
things as fast as we can so you know
credit where credit's due and there's a
lot of credit due and it's also really
important not to make the case that
everything is terrible because it's it's
it's a low-resolution thoughtless case
you know you have to concentrate on
things and differentiate between them so
you know the difference between things
that are problems and things that aren't
because of everything is a problem well
you might as well just sit at home and
drink gin because
nothing you can do about it but you know
the truth of the matter is is that when
we put our minds together we can
actually fix things pretty fast and part
of the necessity that precedes fixing
things is to become informed enough so
that you understand at least to some
minimal degree what you're talking about
so I'm hoping that to some minimal
degree I know what I'm talking about and
if I'm not I'm hoping that Arthur Hanson
who is a real expert on these matters
will correct me so well what's still bad
in the world
well corruptions still bad and it's a
it's a cause of suffering that's
definitely under addressed I think often
for political reasons and there's no
doubt that we have a pollution problem
and I would say that's basically a waste
management problem and it's the kind of
problem that faces really any creature
because all creatures have to deal with
their waste and of course maybe we
produce a bit more of it than we should
because we're pretty smart and we build
lots of things but you know it is part
and parcel of living in a universe where
the primary force is thermodynamic
deterioration you know it's a hell of a
thing to fight so it's not because we're
an 8 li evil that we produce byproducts
it's because life is very complex and
difficult to sustain and we want to live
longer and no wonder and we'd rather
that everyone didn't suffer any more
than they had to and that's probably a
good thing too so we've got our reasons
however when I was going through all of
this you know there was a couple of
things that really stuck out for me and
one of them was the oceanic problem
because well there was a bunch of
reasons the first was because I thought
that data indicating that what we were
doing was damaging was really
incontrovertible as opposed to many of
the issues that you hear about from time
to time or maybe constantly it's very
very clear that we're overfishing and
overfishing dramatically and that we're
doing other things to the oceanic
environment that are definitely not in
our medium or long term interest to say
nothing about the creatures themselves I
also thought that oceanic the oceanic
management problem was an appropriate
problem to consider from a more
practical perspective I mean I thought a
lot about global warming and I'm not
going to talk much about
global warming because that isn't what
I'm here to talk about but one of the
things I did realize about global
warming rapidly was that the error in
the estimates of the likely warming of
the planet over the next 60 years are so
large even if they're done by the best
scientists they're so large that even if
we stopped using anything that produced
carbon dioxide now we would never know
if that actually helped and when I
looked at that I thought well how in the
world are you going to sell something
like that you even if it works you can't
tell if it worked
plus you know that the time course of
improvement is over multiple decades and
everyone uses hydro carbon energy so
it's a real killer to try to address it
seemed to me that it was more logical in
some ways to focus on problems at a
shorter horizon and somewhat more
immediate returns because that way you
can tell if all the effort that you're
putting into solving the problem is
actually having some sort of positive
consequence and the Oceanic management
problems seem to fit into that too was
wasn't intractable it wasn't a problem
that was rapidly disappearing on its own
like world poverty seems to me I don't
think you can speed that up the
disappearance of poverty anymore that
it's being sped up it's sort of hitting
maximum improvement so it sort of falls
into the category of solvable problem
with potentially proper interventions
the other thing is as far as I can tell
there's no losers to fixing this
you know the Oceanic mismanagement
problem is of such magnitude with the
exception of certain species that if we
keep up our rate of fishing for the next
20 years there's not going to be an
awful lot left and that's not going to
be very good for the large corporations
that you know that make their economic
living off the oceans it's be a real
hard on us if we want to eat and then of
course there's the loss of the beauty
and the diversity and and also the
potential to truly transform the nature
of the ecosystems of the ocean in a way
that really won't be good I mean our
planets covered 2/3 by oceans and that's
a lot and we're messing with them in a
really serious way and part of the
reason for that is you know fish or fish
and they've got scales and they're not
that brainian we're going after them
with like 21st century technology you
know we use planes to spot them and
sonar to find out where they are and and
like ultrasonic mapping to to to check
out the structure at the bottom of the
ocean and massive nets and like those
bloody things don't have a chance and
that's not so good
you know it's inappropriate use of
technology now there's some real reasons
for it now
as I said I'm a lay person I read a lot
I probably read about 40 books and the
whole pile of papers on this topic and
others and some of them were really
helpful and these are some of them the
end of the line is a great book and
these are very straightforward books to
read they're very engaging unnatural
history the sea I love that the most
important fish in the sea that's about
this little herring like fish that lives
off the Atlantic coast called the
Manhattan which is kind of an inedible
oily beast of a herring and it at least
one time numbered in the hundreds of
billions it might have been the most
plentiful animal on the surface of the
planet
maybe out numbering all the other fish
and it's at the very bottom of the food
chain and people can't really eat it but
everything else does it one of the
things we're doing with the Manhattan
which seems you know really not all that
bright is vacuuming vacuuming them up
like mr. burns from The Simpsons and
grinding them into fish fertilizer and
spreading them all over the ground you
know when we have all sorts of other
ways of making fertilizer and so you
know we're stripping the whole bottom of
the food chain out of the Atlantic coast
and a lot of that seems to have to do
with political corruption in the eastern
US states so it's a it's a remarkable
book cod I love that - Marko Lansky is a
great author and you know reading about
the devastation of the cod fishery and
the East Coast is just enough to make
the you know bottom fall out of your
heart because it was so damn dumb you
know everybody knew it was coming and
people pretended that it wasn't and we
devastated resource that was really the
pride of the country and also a mainstay
of of the world economy for five six
hundred years you know so it's a great
book and I'm showing you those books
because that's source material for a lot
of what I'm going to tell you now the
first thing I learned
the oceans was that the oceans aren't
that big not when you're talking about
what lives in them because the oceans
actually have two kinds of structure and
one structure they call the pelagic zone
and it only extends 50 miles from the
shore so it's like this little skinny
you know offshoot of the continents
essentially maybe you know it as the
continental shelf it's only about 500
feet deep now that's important because
because it's only that deep light can
get to the bottom from the Sun and so
you need light for things to grow
especially plants and if plants can't
grow then the animals can't eat anything
and then there aren't any animals so it
turns out that all the all the life
fundamentally you know with a bit of an
exception is within 50 miles from shore
and so and in these areas that are only
you know 500 feet deep or less now if
you look at this map the light blue
areas there are the pelagic zone and you
know they look pretty big up in the
Arctic remember this is all stretched
out because it's not a very intelligent
projection but all the dark blue stuff
man that's deep two miles deep on
average and it can be 11,000 feet deep
in places and the problem with that is
it's really dark no light gets down
there it's really cold it's not much
above freezing it's really high pressure
like higher pressure than the surface of
Venus and so it's not that hospitable
for life there's not a lot around there
and you know the problem with that at
least in part is well a that's most of
the ocean and B it's mostly empty but
because it's cold and dark the things
that do live there well they're not very
well understood but they also grow very
fast so if you do fish them and we are
fishing them then you know you fish them
and it's like harvesting the trees that
grow up in the Arctic you know they take
forever to grow back so and as we fished
out the pelagic zone which were which
we're doing at a fairly rapid rate we've
increasingly turned to the neritic zone
with especially with trawlers that can
now reach 2,000 meters down to the
bottom of the ocean and you know it's
not high-quality food generally speaking
but the problem too is we don't
understand it well and it seems quite
easy to
devastate so anyway so that's a useful
thing to know is but there really isn't
that much food bearing ocean and that a
lot of the planet is sort of covered by
water that's too dark deep and cold to
be of a lot of use here's the things
that really broke my heart I think
reading this um because one of the
things that these books taught me was
just how much there was before we took
it and like I said I'm not an anti-human
in any way but the way this struck me
was that it was a catastrophic aesthetic
and and spiritual loss a loss of the
absolute bounty of the planet and the
sort of thing that that evokes in the
viewer or the experience are the same
sort of thing that maybe is a VOC when
you look up at the sky and see the vast
array of star is sort of spread out
before us the magnificence of nature and
we're denying ourselves the privilege of
experiencing that increasingly so let me
tell you what it was like when the
Europeans first came to North America
and you want to remember that this is
even after the Native Americans had done
a fair bit of fishing and also after the
Europeans had already pretty much fished
out their waters completely sturgeon
while sturgeons of prehistoric fish it's
been around about sixty million years or
so and they get really long and babe
they get so big you have to haul them
out of rivers with oxen they can weigh
1200 pounds and they're hardly any on
the Atlantic coast anymore I don't know
if there are any there's some still in
northwestern Canada they live in the
Fraser River for example this was the
Potter Mac River in 1760 Potomac I guess
sturgeon and shad are in such prodigious
numbers that in one day within the space
of two miles only some gentlemen in
canoes caught about 600 of the former
that was sturgeon with hooks which they
let down to the bottom and drew up at a
venture when they perceived them to rub
against the fish and of the latter shad
about five thousand have been caught in
one single hole of the net so it was
possible to catch 600 sturgeon in one
day I don't imagine that six hundred
sturgeon are caught
now in the whole world in a year alibi
for herring in 1728 this is from William
bird when they spawn all streams and
waters are completely filled with them
and one might believe when he sees such
terrible amounts of them that there was
this great a supply of herring as there
is water in words it is unbelievable
indeed indescribable as also
incomprehensible what quantity is found
there one must behold oneself there are
many evil pictures during of the herring
run near the coast where people would
put a halberd which was a kind of double
headed axe with honor on a pole in the
water and it would stand up because
there are so many herring around the
herring themselves were packed in so
tightly that the thing would stay up in
the water William would the halibut is
not much unlike a place or turbot some
being two yards long and one wide and a
foot thick the plenty of better fish so
they have plenty of better fish than
halibut when the Europeans first came to
North America made them little esteemed
except the head and fins which stood or
baked is very good these halibuts be
little set by while based basses in
season thornback and skates is given to
the dogs being not counted worth the
dressing in many places you should also
know that when the Europeans first came
to North America salmon and lobster fell
in the same category so there were laws
in New England about how many lobster
you could feed convicts or slaves in a
week because it was you know it was like
feeding them bugs as far as the New
Englanders were concerned you know when
salmon was so plentiful it was basically
a junk fish so these things that we now
regard essentially as delicacies
especially while wild salmon were there
an absolutely unbelievable number so I
lived in Boston for a little while and I
used to go up to the coast there is a
place there called Cape Anne which is up
where the whaling communities used to be
because it was a big whaling area and we
used to go to this beautiful beach that
was like seven miles long and 300 yards
wide and it was absolutely pristine
gorgeous place and they the history of
the area recounts the name what happened
to the beach after Nor'easters
nor'easter is like a hurricane except
it's the you know northern
version of a hurricane he said after a
good nor'easter which happened around
Boston pretty often the beach there
would be covered with shellfish and
other fish three feet deep and 100 yards
wide and seven miles long so that what
after there was a nor'easter the whole
area would wreak for months because of
all the rotting fish and self shellfish
I went to Cape Anne to the beach one
time after a nor'easter and walked about
three miles I found one starfish an
empty lobster trap and a half dead
horseshoe crab and that was it and
normally walking on that beach there was
nothing at all so that's the degree to
which the area had been essentially
devastated priest Andrea Bernal des with
Christopher Columbus throughout that
voyage they saw that there were many
Turtles and very large but in those
twenty leagues they saw very many more
for the sea was thick with them and they
were of the largest so numerous that it
would seem that the ships would run
aground on them and whereas if bathing
in them the Indians valued them highly
in regard them is very good to eat and
healthy and savory figure there were
something on the neighborhood of two to
four hundred million Turtles in the
Caribbean and they're pretty much all
gone
sea otters from San Francisco to the
Santa Clara estuary the ground appeared
covered with black sheets due to the
great quantity of otters which were
there the disappearance of otters
because they're almost completely wiped
out
eliminated kelp forests because the
Otters ate the urchins which grazed on
the kelp and removing the kelp forests
wiped out Steller's sea cow which was a
30-foot marine animal similar to the
manatee except much larger it was wiped
out while hunting along habitat and
hunting twenty-eight years after its
identification by Europeans from
California a late 1850s a thousand gray
whales a day passed along the shore
between December 15th and February 1st
so there are valid reports from all over
the world before the whaling industry
really kicked in of whales being about
as common as porpoises are now when you
see them swarming around the Front's of
boats so there were whales absolute
everywhere so you imagine that a
thousand a day for a for basically a
three-month period so Harry
1776 when the main body has arrived its
breadth and depth is such as to alter
the very appearance of the ocean it is
divided into distinct columns of five or
six miles in length and three or four
broad well the water before them curls
up as it forced out of its bed
sometimes they sink for the space of ten
or fifteen minutes then rising into the
surface and a great weather reflective
variety of splendid colors like a field
be spangled with purple golden easier
the whole water seems alive and it seems
so blocked with them to a great distance
that the number seems inexhaustible the
there are so many turtles swimming
towards the islands and the Caribbeans
that when the sailors used to get lost
in the fog if they were close enough
they could they could sail to land by
hearing the turtles splash in the water
along with their herring the herring
schools of the great magnitude there
were immense number of predators because
of course the herring is a primary food
for other fish and so there were massive
schools of sharks and so on that would
come along feed on them haddock from
Goldsmiths in 1810 they'd annually visit
the British coast ensures that sometimes
extend along the shore a hundred miles
in length and 300 miles in breadth in
1855 forty-three fishing schooners from
Beverly Massachusetts caught more cod
south of Nova Scotia on the Scotian
shelf so these are just sailing ships
then the entire Canadian fleet caught
there in 1999 six years later
thirty-four schooners landed more cod on
the Maine coast between Penobscot Bay
and Grand Manan that were caught in the
entire Gulf of Maine from Cape Cod to
Canada in 1999 so well if you read those
books that I showed you they're just
full of accounts of precisely that sort
of makes painful reading you know
there's Kerr Lasky also wrote a book
called the big oyster which is about New
York and he talked about which has a big
they used to be like
Herr Lansky claims that the average
sized oyster 300 years ago was as big as
a dinner plate and had to be cut into
four pieces before it could be water and
so Chesapeake Bay was an absolutely
staggering masterpiece of natural Plenty
and it's pretty much been reduced to
nothing as well so it makes pretty
painful reading and one of the things I
also learned about this and I'll talk
about this a little bit later is you
know when you hear estimates of fish
stock depletion you hear things like 95
percent since the beginning of the 20th
century but lots of these writers claim
that the fish stocks had already been
reduced by 95 percent or more by the
beginning of the 20th century so we're
looking at a 95 percent reduction in a
95 percent reduction so you know that
kind of hurts now there's a lot of
reasons for this one of them is called
the tragedy of the Commons and the
tragedy of the Commons is well imagine
that there is a field on which anybody
can graze their sheep while the logical
thing to do is to get your sheep out
there and let them eat all the grass
before the next guy gets his sheep out
there and eats all the grass right and
so the tragedy of Commons is that when
there's no fixed ownership of a resource
it makes sense economically for the
person who gets first access to the
resource to take as much of it as they
can because anything they leave at least
in principle is going to be taken by
someone else and historically and until
at least 1978 the open ocean was only
seven miles offshore that's where the
where the national jurisdiction ended
the rest of the sea was regarded as you
know free territory in a sense so people
can take whatever they wanted and you
know you can see that as a legal and a
structural problem so that's one of the
main contributors another contributor
right now to to the continued decimation
of the world's fish stocks and one of
the things that makes regulation
difficult is what's being described as
technological creep so you say you might
say well you know maybe you can limit
your boat to 40 the boats that are
allowed to fish to 40 feet in length or
something like that instead of these
massive factory boats that go out and
you know sit on the ocean for my
vacuum up everything in your trailer the
problem with technological creep which
sounds like a you know maybe some kind
of computer programmer who's looking
lurking in the bushes is is that even
your 40-foot bill keeps getting
outfitted with better and better
technology right because as you know how
fast our technology increases and so you
can have the same size boat that you had
10 years ago and the things like ten
times as deadly as it was because you
know you're outfitted with the latest
gear and you can understand why the
fishermen are driven to that but and
it's another structural problem that
that adds to this general overall
problem the use of this sort of
space-age technology has had a pretty
catastrophic consequence too so we're
doing something they call let's see I'm
gonna yeah fishing down the food chain
so the way the food chains are set up is
there's like you know plankton at the
bottom and they eat whatever they can
get their little hands on and they're
often not you don't actually have
handsome you know they also use
photosynthesis and there's there at the
bottom of the food chain there's
billions of the things being whales eat
them some whales and then you know
little fish eat those and then bigger
fish eat the little fish and bigger fish
eat
you know the medium-sized fish and so on
all the way up to things like sharps and
swordfish and tuna and human beings now
what we're basically doing we tend to
like the fish that are higher up on the
on the food chain so we tend to like the
taste of predatory fish because they're
hard muscled and now the problem with
that is that the higher you are you are
up in the food chain the fewer there can
be of you in part because you know
you're your primary sources of food are
limited by this by this pyramid
phenomena as we've got better and better
from a technological perspective at
catching fish what's happened is we keep
we are fishing down the food chain we go
from the great big fish at the top like
the Sharks about 70 million a year of
which right now are killed for shark fin
soup and that's that's a lot of sharks
seventy million a year you know we're
going to run out of sharks in no time
flat if we keep things up at that rate
and so we fish down the food chain we
take the big predators first and they're
the most valuable fish and then we go
after what they go after and then we go
after what that fish is going after and
we go out farther Rafi
when we go out into the deep ocean and
we find places that no one's fished
before but were so damn good at it now
that the time to exhaustion of the new
fish species from the time we discovered
is about 15 years so we can discover a
new species which is often given even if
it's half inedible it's given a real
marketable name we go after it was face
age technology and wipe it down to more
than a - less than 85% of its previous
numbers within 15 years we're really
deadly and so you know as soon as we
discover something plus there's so many
of us that the things in serious trouble
in pretty much no time flat there is
there has been a global decline in the
world's catch ever since about 1998 if
you control for red China's data because
the Chinese from what I've been able to
determine tend to inflate their
production numbers I mean that's a
standard trick in totalitarian states
but there even though we swear switching
to different species and you know we're
pretty damn good at that we haven't been
able to halt the decline in overall
catch despite the fact that you know our
technology has improved a lot we're
going after other species and that's not
a good thing and the other thing that's
really worth noting about fish and this
is one of the things that convinced me
that there really was a problem was you
guys might know about the bet that was
made by a Stanford biologist Paul
Ehrlich and an economist whose name I
don't remember in about 1968 and Paul
Ehrlich had written this book called the
Population Bomb where he predicted that
you know we were all going to starve to
death by the year 2000 and the
economists always disagree with the
biologist because economists think we're
real smart and can think our way out of
everything and you know so far they've
been you know reasonably right the
biologists say well it's just a time
they will melt mel Fussell wind
eventually and who knows but this
economists bet Eric that by the year
2000 commodity prices would have gone
down instead of up because Eric's idea
was everything's getting scarce so from
1968 to the year 2000 all our
commodities which are somewhat scarce
are going to increase in price
well Eric got stormed the commodity
prices plummeted between 1968 mm so the
economists had
you know had beat them in no uncertain
terms but the one thing that didn't work
out that way is seafood I mean things
like cod used to be cheap right seafood
used to be cheap fish and chips that was
the cheapest thing you could buy on the
menu well it's not like that anymore
seafood is expensive and you know bloody
well when something gets expensive that
there actually isn't that much of it
anymore it's a really good marker so you
know we have global decline Global cash
declining figures allied with pretty
hard economic data that fish is a lot
more expensive than it used to be plus
we're harvesting we're harvesting
species that people wouldn't have even
considered edible a hundred years ago I
mean 200 years ago they were complaining
about halibut and feeding it to their
dogs it's like that's a high quality
fish by our standards so there's no
doubt that this is a real this is a real
phenomenon
and there's other awful things that
really are kind of difficult to tolerate
when you read about them and trawling is
one of them and here here's a nice
description of trolling basically what a
trawl does is this a huge net that's put
behind a really big boat and the net is
weighted down and has rollers there's a
bunch of different kinds of them it has
rollers and you put it on the bottom of
the ocean it sort of digs down to a
depth of about eight inches and then you
just drag the thing and you drag it till
the net fills up and well what does it
fill up with well whatever's down there
coral so especially now that they're
fishing out the deeper areas of the
ocean all the corals coming up 300 pound
chunks of it maybe they figure it takes
10,000 years to grow and you know that's
habitat for for fish you run on a
trawler over an area there's nothing
left of it it takes everything you haul
it up what happens you take you ten
percent of the damn fish that's in there
that you want to eat you throw 90
percent back because that's what you
have to do by law so the bycatch so to
speak which is what you don't want is 90
percent back it goes into the water now
remember I showed you the continental
shelf there's not that much of it what
we've trolled most of it so when that
isn't stopped
the trawlers are getting bigger there's
something they called a super trawler
that was heading down to Australia
despite a lot of you know public outcry
because the Australians are fairly
sensitive about this sort of thing you
know they're bigger and bigger and
bigger all the time and that's partly
because they're you know because they
can and partly because they're chasing a
diminishing resource so you imagine what
would happen if you you know went
through a you know a nice bit of
grassland or a national park with a net
300 feet high and it was you know
dragged through by tractors you just
take everything trees deer moose birds
insects everything pull out the things
you can eat let everything else rot
Jesus if it was happening on land people
would be shorting out and running around
in circles screaming but it's happening
on you at the bottom of the ocean and
no-one can see it and it's not just
happening once there's lots of places in
the North Sea which used to be clear and
is no longer clear it's muddy because of
the trawling at least in part because of
the disturbance of the ocean floor that
place has been trolled like three or
four times so you know obviously that's
not going to work for very long
so here's there here's the description
picture a 2,000 horsepower trawler
targeting place or soul pulling a beam
trawl mounted with a rotating tickler
with rotating tickler chains across the
featureless fans and gravels of the
southern north sea the weighted trawl
and its chains designed to beat flatfish
out of the sheltering mud smashes up
everything it does not catch
particularly the burrowing animals in
the sediment disturbing them at depths
of up to 6 inches European Union
scientists have calculated that up to 16
pounds of marine animals are killed by
beam trolls to produce one pound of
marketable Soul sea urchins hermit crabs
brittle stars and razor shells are
killed or having part of their shells
opened made vulnerable to predators
starfish tend to be the survivors losing
a leg or two but escaping the net the
winner in heavily trolled areas are
usually crabs which move in from other
areas to eat damaged creatures and worms
that take over from the easily damaged
by valves a scientists have concluded
that most parts of the southern North
Sea have been disturbed by a beam
at least once a year the damage caused
by fishing is estimated at 100,000 times
greater than that of oil or gas
exploration so it's pretty much total
devastation so you know that's kind of
distressing they estimate about 25
percent of the world's total catch is
hauled in by trawls so that just doesn't
seem like a particularly intelligent way
of going about things now because the
whole shelf is being trialed and there's
not a hell of a lot left there they've
developed trials that can go down to
2,000 meters and 2,000 meters you know
that's getting to be a mile and a half
that's that's close to the average depth
of the deepest part of the ocean now
when you go way down in the ocean
there's no a lot there as I said but
there are places of the ocean floor that
are seem out so they sort of poke up and
when they poke up currents come up them
and there's a lot of food on the sea
mount areas and they can map those out
really nicely down with the deep sea
trials they just go to the sea mounts
and take everything that's there so a
purse scenes are also pretty devastating
especially when you combine them with
spawning airplanes because the spawning
airplanes go off the coast too they find
a you know a school and then the scenes
the Saints come in and they take the
whole school so you know that's also not
really particularly a promising thing to
be happening so then the next
problematic form of fishing seems to be
maybe longline fishing and so long lines
are pretty much exactly that they sound
like they're very long fishing lines and
very long leads up to 40 miles long and
with 30 hooks per mile and so that's
1,200 hooks and so you know they're
often catching the kind of fish that
you'd like to eat but they catch a lot
of other things too like tens of
thousands of seabirds and tens of
thousands of turtles and all sorts of
things and sharks and all sorts of
things that you know will eat anything
that's on a baited hook so the bycatch
problem with longline fishing is also
horrendous so that's kind of that's kind
of you know miserable to our hand as
well and then you know there's this
thing I mentioned a little bit earlier
about the Manhattan and that stuff that
was a
distressing book to read because they're
the Manhattan because they're at the
bottom of the food chain down you know
down down near where the little fish are
there oh and Men hadn't interestingly
enough our vegetarian most fish aren't
vegetarian but these guys are vegetarian
so that's what puts them at the bottom
of the food chain they also take a lot
of garbage out of the water because
they're vegetarian and so if there's
algal blooms or something like that
which there often is because of nitrogen
runoff from fertilizers from the land
that the Manhattan will go in there and
clean it up and then all the other fish
will eat them but they take the men out
now to turn them into fertilizer and as
I said already you know that seems to be
served at least in part by corruption in
the East Coast states they do the same
thing in Denmark with this thing called
the sand eel and it's another one of
these ugly little things that you know
people wouldn't normally eat but
everything else does and there's a lot
of them they're sort of like the men hot
and they breed like mad but they've been
catching them catching those up a storm
do it and often burning them for oil so
well and then there's oxido Canada
Canada is by no means an ecological
paradise like we like to pride ourselves
on the idea that you know we're there
sort of great north with our massive
forests and our care for the environment
most that's pretty much rubbish so for
example we have a far a smaller portion
of our territory devoted to national
parks than the Americans do despite the
fact that what 95 percent of the country
is basically uninhabited so that's a
pretty shocking statistic and the
Americans have done a much better job of
managing their fisheries than us and you
know we should have been shocked into
what embarrassed action in 1992 when
this happened so you know the cod
fishery off the Grand Banks had been
there for 400 years and it was really
one of the world's remarkable treasures
and around before I guess 1978 the limit
national sovereignty I think was seven
miles it's four or seven miles I can't
remember exactly what and you know the
Spaniards Spaniards and the Portuguese
and and lots of European fishing boats
were in the Grand Banks fishing like
which of course they've been doing for
really almost 600 years the Basques
might have even got there before
Christopher Columbus and not told
anybody because they'd like to have all
those fish you know and Basques they're
pretty sneaky people so anyways you know
so the Canadian government made a big
fuss about the fact that all these
foreigners were out there taking out the
cod and they were part of the the
political force that got the national
sovereignty zone extended to 200 miles
offshore so the candidate had managed
its own cod stocks and of course we do
it responsibly well the first thing that
happened was the federal government
modernized the Newfoundland fishing
fleet and equipped it with you know
really outstanding boats and the second
thing that happened was we took all the
fish and so by net one you see what
happened by basically by 1992 so two
billion fish that's the estimate that's
a lot of fish equal and weight to the
entire Canadian population and these
caught man they were magnificent animals
they figured the ones that were there
when the Europeans first came over to
North America or something like five
feet late in length more or less on
average and teeth three feet around
these were big fish you know they're
both the size of a person and they came
in massive massive schools and no one
really knows why they haven't come back
there's a couple hypotheses one is you
know fish in schools are like zebras you
don't see zebras lone zebras rain
roaming the Serengeti you know what you
see is big clumps of zebras because
they're herd animals and they really are
herd animals which means the herd is
their environment and so they can't live
away from a herd more any less than
people can and it looks like COD or sort
of like that another fish that live in
schools so for example one of the things
that happens with Cod schools is that
first of all there's a lot of subspecies
of cod and we don't know how old the
schools are but some of the schools
might be who knows 150,000 years old as
superorganism and they seem to actually
kind of know the ocean in which they
swim as a collective unit and so they
know where to go eat and they know where
you know they they know their habitat
and more importantly the cod range
themselves in
so that the big Carter in the middle and
the little Carter sort of outside and
then the Predators pick off the little
Cod but they're useless anyways because
they're too young to breed so the school
is structured so that the big Carter
protective second when the card mate
they actually use the school as a mating
structure so they organize the mating
routines on the outside of the school
structure and so what that implies is
that if you blow out the structure of
the school then the Kahn don't know what
to do and that's one potential reason
they haven't really managed to come back
there's others one being perhaps that if
you really devastate a population then
maybe you change the ecological
conditions of the environment because it
turns out that the way an ecosystem sets
itself up is dependent to some degree on
which creature gets there first sort of
which creature gets there in what order
and so if you wipe population like the
card out low enough then other animals
move in to get the niche and that's it
the card can't come back now there's
other theories too you know some of
which have to do with ocean warming but
the point is we've left the card alone
kind of because people are still allowed
to fish a lot more for Cod than you'd
think
we've kind of left them alone for 20
years and the consequence has been
pretty minimal especially for an animal
that you know fish they lay a lot of
eggs it's not like they're it's not like
they're they're not able to reproduce
they certainly know how to do that so so
you know you think we might learn
something from this but it doesn't
really appear that we did and the other
thing that really struck me is
mind-boggling when I was going through
this material was exactly Canada's
record which was so embarrassing that it
was again it was like a personal blow so
in 1910 I'm going to pretty much fold up
with this in 1992 which was about when
the cod fishery collapsed Canada
promised to protect 20% of its oceanic
territory so the idea was to put aside
chunks of oceanic territory sort of like
national parks you know where the
animals that live there in the
ecosystems would be protected so that
they could come back because you know
fish come back pretty fast if you leave
them alone I read something very
think about this very fact um you know
how you heard and maybe this is wrong
but I read it several places you know
how you heard that the whole Gulf of
Mexico oil spill was such a catastrophe
for fish yeah well there were more fish
the year after this filled in the year
before and the reason for that is no one
fished so that's you know that's a
pretty peculiar statistic but it shows
you two things a how many fish we take
and B how damn fast the fish can come
back if you leave them alone the same
thing happened in the North Sea in World
War two was pretty much fished out
before World War two but no one was
fishing during World War two because of
German u-boats and there was a lot of
fish in the North Sea again after World
War two so if you leave the things alone
for a while they can come back Canada
promised to protect at least 20% of its
oceanic territory by 2012 in writing in
a series of major international forums
where Canada signed treaties in 1992
2002 2003 and 2005 so not only did we
promise we promised frequently and in
writing less than 1% is currently
protected despite the fact that Canada
has one of the longest international
coastlines in the world and is also home
to multiple you know how there are
ecological zones because each little
geographic area has its own peculiar
characteristics and so really what you
need is you need to set aside a
protected area that are sort of
representative of all these different
ecological zones and we have plenty of
those ecological zones zero action 1% of
our oceanic territory is protected
that's it and you can fish in 95% of
that so what we've done in the aftermath
of the great cod catastrophe looks to me
to be pretty much absolutely nothing and
what's weird about that and at least in
part I mean Canada is a complicated
place but the Australians have actually
protected 20% of their oceanic area and
have promised 20% more recently and they
actually seem to mean it which is about
a third as much territory as Australia
actually has so it is actually possible
to set aside what are essentially
national parks in the in the ocean
and let the damn fish come back and in
principle at least that would also be
good for the fishermen because they can
hang around the edges of the parks and
you know the fish don't know where the
boundaries are they can scoop them up
once they breed again
so it's a rather cataclysmic and
staggering saga of insane mismanagement
and you know it's not there's not much
point pointing the finger one place or
another because you know it's pretty
much everybody's fault but it sure seems
to me to be one of those things that you
got to think about as being uh it's it's
it's hauntingly foolish because all of
that could be there why wouldn't that be
a good thing and you know if there was
the political will in Canada it could be
done because other countries have done
it and for some reason this is just not
and on the radar issue even though it's
a real issue this is actually happening
it's really not good it's happening a
lot it's going to get worse we're not
going to have a lot of fish to eat the
oceans are going to be a pretty barren
and dismal place and we can actually do
something about it so so that's why I
decided to do this talk even though I
don't really know a lot about the oceans
you know it seems to me that the
situation is always dangerous talking
about things when you sort of know
something and mostly you don't but it
seems to me that the situation with the
oceans is so obviously not good that you
actually don't have to be an expert to
notice and so what can be done about it
well you know the only I think the
marine protected areas are a good idea
and look you know that we have examples
of countries doing it and it seems to
work everyone's already figured out that
it's a pretty good idea with regards to
national parks on land no one seems to
really dispute that although you know we
could have some more national parks so
what's the big problem about having them
out in the ocean you know
preserve some of the coastline and to
let the fish have a fighting chance and
this we don't want to have them around
you know and what we're facing in some
ways well they're starting to process
jellyfish for food because as we get rid
of the fish that the whole ecosystem
starts to turn back to what it was like
400 million years ago before there were
any fish and there were lots of
invertebrates and you know we could have
an ocean full of invertebrates and I
hear they press up into hockey stick
hockey puck sized discs pretty nicely
they don't have a lot of taste and I
suppose you'd have to be a pretty good
chef to make them edible but we probably
won't run out of jellyfish during our
life so I don't know maybe it wouldn't
be a bad idea to pen a note to your MP
or to the Minister of Fisheries or and
just note that you know destroying a
resource that we could actually enjoy
aesthetically and practically that
destroying that seems to be not
anybody's best interest and that it's
actually happening at a pretty rapid
rate so I guess that's partly what Finn
is aiming out and partly why I decided
to do this talk and also to get involved
in to invite dr. Hansen who's going to
who really knows what he's talking about
who's going to speak next so we should
take a 10-minute break and then we'll
return and have dr. Hansen speak
there'll be a question and answer period
at the end of the after at the end of
dr. Hansen's talking thank